Hi! I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 1
of the Lip Reading Challenge,
designed to help you practice
and develop your lip
reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and
tricks on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity to relationships
in all areas of your life.
Today you're going to get three mangoes with one stone,
and by that I mean
there's a way to be
efficient when you're learning how to read lips.
You can put three mangoes in your bucket with
the sounds P, B, and M.
To make these sounds, your lips meet and then part.
There's almost like a puff of air when the mouth opens.
Watch these words:
Park
Bark
Mark.
You may have noticed
that these words look exactly the same!
If you saw these words in isolation,
meaning they're not in a sentence,
you would not be able to tell them apart.
But
these words don't
sound the same at all.
Would you really confuse them?
Yeah, you might.
The difference between
a P and a B is
only a fraction of a second
of vibration of your vocal cords.
If your attention
is elsewhere for that fraction of a second,
or if there's noise in the background covering
up a word or two, you might confuse them.
I do find it helpful to know that there's a good
reason to misunderstand when I get off track.
So you know that you can't distinguish
between Park, Bark and Mark.
But if you saw them in a sentence, you'd be able
to figure it out. You can develop this skill to
the point where you can do it in real time. So
if the first thing you see doesn't make sense,
you can do a quick substitution in your
mind and come up with something that fits!
I'll give you an example from my own life.
I'm deaf, and I have a cochlear implant in one ear
and a hearing aid in the other.
I wasn't wearing either (of them) when I saw,
"You should coping."
You should coping?? That doesn't make sense!
What was actually said is, "You should go big."
Both COPING and Go BIG start and end with
invisible sounds.
The C in COPING is invisible,
as is the G in Go Big.
At the end of these words, the -NG found in COPING
and the G in BIG are also invisible.
And everything else looks the same.
So I ended up getting it by making that quick substitution and also because of a gesture.
He said, "You should go big."
I want you to learn to make substitutions
in today's lesson. Let's try it. I'm going
to say a sentence with a P, B, or M error
and I want you to make the substitution.
I'll give you an example. If you saw, "Have
you ever been to Banff National Mark?"
Then you would think, okay, so Banff National Mark
isn't right, how about Banff National Bark? No, that's not it.
Okay, Banff National Park.
You see how that goes.
For the next 10 sentences, I'm not going to give you the answers
but the answers are written below in the video caption section just below the video frame.
If you need more time, just pause the video and repeat.
I'm going to jump in every once in a while
and give you some information on lip reading theory.
Are you ready?
Number 1: I have a great recipe for barbecue rims.
Number 2: My cub is empty.
Number 3: Ugh,  I'm at the end of my Rome!
Number 4: I don't let my met up on the couch.
Number 5: Please, think no poor about it!
Number 6: Oh, it's so nice to beat you, finally!
In this example, there's a mismatch between
my facial expression and body language and
the word "beat."
This mismatch is a clue.
Was it sarcasm? Or did you misunderstand?
So in this way, lip reading becomes about also
looking at the facial expression and the body
language and any gestures involved.
For this reason, the more correct term is speech reading.
I don't think it matters which term you
use: lip reading (or) speech reading.
As long as you make use of all the
information that's available to you--
so, facial expression, body language,
gestures, and also the teeth, the tongue,
the lips, and the jaw.
Let's keep going.
Number 7: The baby sat on his mother's lamb.
Number 8: In yoga class, we chanted home.
The H is invisible. Watch: home.
Number 9: My hair is a mess-- I need a hope.
The H is invisible, remember?
What is another invisible sound that you learned about in this lesson
that you could put at the beginning of HOPE and then make a P, B, or M substitution at the end?
I'll say it again: My hair is a mess-- I need a hope.
Number 10:  Same thing as number 9.
Make a substitution of the invisible sound at the beginning
and then make a P, B, or M substitution at the end.
Kelp! I'm being chased by a wild pore!
If this exercise did not make sense to you, read
the answers in the description section below the
video frame and then repeat the lesson. There's
also some extra substitution practice for any
keeners out there that are alongside the answers.
I love keeners (sign for same).
One more tip. P, B and M are homophenes.
Homophenes are groups of sounds that look alike. And when we're learning how to lip read,
we learn about the sounds in groups
of homophenes, where possible.
It's efficient, but it also calls attention
to the fact that sometimes
it's understandable to misunderstand.
And then we can deal with it by making that quick substitution
when the first thing we see does not make sense!
Remember the invisible sounds that we
learned about today.
Make a list:
The H,
the hard C as in coping, or the K sound;
the G,
and the -NG at the end of coping.
There are others, so just keep a running
list and we'll add to it in future lessons.
Tomorrow, we're going to practice actually
lip reading P, B and M sounds in sentences.
Until then, what word looks like mango?
The word I'm thinking of is not exactly the same, but it looks pretty close.
I really look forward to hearing how you did on these exercises.
Please be sure to comment and
share any questions that you might have.
Be sure to like the video
and subscribe to my channel,
so that you can follow the next nine
days of our lip reading challenge!
So, I'll see you tomorrow!
It's time to eat.
I think I'll make a smoothie.
Bye!